Guide to the George Marion Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.045
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Marion Photographs
1930s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marion, George, 1905-
ALBA.PHOTO.045
0.75 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
George Marion (1905-1955) was a journalist, author, and Communist Party activist. In 1936, Marion went to Spain to cover the Spanish Civil War for the Daily Worker and the New Masses. The images in this collection were accrued by Marion in the course of his work as a journalist in Spain. The collection contains group photographs and portraits of members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Republican military leaders, Communist Party leaders, military vehicles, political demonstrations/rallies, Spanish munitions workers, and street scenes.
145 b & w Photographs sized from 3 x 4.5 to 9.5 x 3.25 inches and 20 black and white negatives sized from 2.5 x 2.5 to 4 x 5 inches.
Provenance
The Marion Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, formerly housed at Brandeis University, by Elizabeth Craney Marion, George Marion's second wife, in 1983. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
George Marion was a journalist, author, and Communist Party activist. For further biographical information on George Marion and to review the scope and contents of his manuscript collection see,
The Guide to the George Marion Papers, ALBA 45.
Marion accrued the images in this collection during his tenure as a correspondent for the Daily Worker and the New Masses. The majority of the images were procured by Marion from the photographic bureau, Photo Mayo, Madrid. Two photographs are credited to D. Kraman. The images in the Marion Photograph Collection were separated from Marion’s manuscript materials in the course of processing.
Scope and Content Note
The George Marion Photograph Collection includes 145 black and white photographs of varying sizes including: 3 x 4.5 inches, 3.5 x 4.75 inches, 6.5 x 4.5 inches, 6.75 x 4.5 inches and 9.5 x 3.25 inches. The twenty negatives are two sizes. Sixteen negatives are 2.5 x 2.5 inches and four negatives are 4 x 5 inches. The negatives are stored separately from the prints, in Box 2.
Series I: The 145 black and white prints are arranged alphabetically by topic and most are photographs taken in Spain during the Civil War. Approximately three-fourths are attributed to the photographic bureau, Photo Mayo, Madrid. One-half of the images are portraits and one-half are photos of soldiers in combat and at rest. The collection includes vivid combat images in addition to portraits of Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteers, Republican military leaders including General Jose Miaja, Communist Party leaders including Raphael Alberti, José Diaz, Enrique Lister Forjan, Carlos Contreras (alias of Vittorio Vidali), and Rafael Herche, military and transport vehicles, political demonstrations/rallies, Spanish munitions workers, and street scenes. Three of the transport vehicles bear the inscription “U.H.P.” which stands for Unión de Hermanos Proletarios (United Proletarian Brothers), a slogan first used during the Asturian miners' uprising of October 1934. All of the photographs except two were taken in Spain. Of the two photographs taken outside of Spain, one is a group photo onboard the transport ship Ile de France and the other is a photographic postcard depicting the Fuenta de Quijote in Chapultepec, Mexico.
Series II: Negatives arranged alphabetically by topic. The twenty negatives are contained in a separate box from the photographs. Nineteen of the negatives have matching prints. The negative that does not match any prints is a portrait of an unidentified seated male.
The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 45:1:1:1. Negatives are numbered in the same fashion and if there is a matching print, the print number is listed below the negative number.
Arrangement
Folders arranged alphabetically by topic in the Prints and Negatives series.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I: Prints
II: Negatives
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Marion Papers, ALBA 45
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Barcelona (Spain); Negatives (photographic); Seville (Spain); Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Miaja Menant, José, 1878-1958; Kraman, D. (photographer).; Díaz, José, 1896-1942; Vidali, Vittorio.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Galan, Francisco.; Herche, Rafael.; Líster, Enrique.; Alberti, Rafael, 1902-1999; Marion, George, 1905-; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Photographs
  - Alberti, Raphael: Communist Poet/Minister for Public Education [?], 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Group: Embarking for Spain, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arconada, Giorla and Felipe, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asaña, I.R., 1930s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Athletic Activities/Events, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - At the Front: Combat, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ballesteros, Navarro, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bombed Buildings: Barcelona and [?], 1930s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carrillo, Santiago [?], 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Castro, Enrique [?]: Commandante, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Casualties, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Civilians: Portraits, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Coll, Antonio: Frente Popular, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contreras, Carlos aka Vittorio Vidali: Italian Communist, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - De la Funete, Soledad, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Demonstrations/Political Rallies/Political Graffiti, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Diaz, José: Partido Comunista, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Farmers/Farming, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Galan, Francisco: Partido Comunista, Colonel, Commander of Cartagena Naval Base, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Giron: Portrait, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Herche, Rafael: Politburo Member, Education and Fine Arts Minister/Education and Health Minister, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hernandez, Jesus: Partido Comunista, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lister Forjan, Enrique: Communist Militia Leader, Commander of 5th Regiment, later Colonel, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lomoneda, [?], 1930s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Medical Personnel, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miaja, Jose [?]: General and Commander of Madrid Army, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Military Ranks/Insignia, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Military/Transport Vehicles, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Nicoletti, [?]: Commander, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - On the Barricades, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photographic Postcard: Fuenta de Quijote; Chapultepec, Mexico, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sailors, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Soldiers: Group Shots (non-combat), 1930s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Soldiers: Militia Women, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Soldiers: Portraits, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Spanish Children, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Spanish Civil War Poster: Photographic Reproduction, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Spanish Workers, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Street Scenes: Barcelona, Seville, and [?], 1930s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Thorez, Maurice [?]: French Communist Leader, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Weila, Harry and Wilson, Al: Brigade Members, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Series II: Negatives
  - Matched Negatives, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unmatched Negative, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 2)